Hello friends, my name is Sachin and
today I am going to discuss with you
about the waiting period. Friends, our
Health Insurance Avengers series is going on in
which we have
covered all the topics related to health insurance and today we are going to cover the
waiting period. So friends,
why do we want to discuss about the waiting period
because this
is such a topic, this is such a point due to which
more than 50% of the claims are rejected in the entire industry.
People are
not aware about this whether they will get the
claim for this disease or not
and when they do not know this and
they go to the hospital for treatment,
when they come to know that the
claim for this disease will not be available under their policy
and then that is the plain result,
there some people say to the companies that you were
not told, they add from this point
that why did you not tell us
and then it becomes
sour due to a lot of problems. So friends, it is important to understand this waiting
period, firstly it will give
you the Avengers
and secondly if you have taken any  If you already have health
insurance, then check your policy to
see what kind of waiting
period is there in it. If you are taking it, then
check what kind of
waiting period is there in it also. So friends, before moving forward,
I want to tell you that if
you are new to my channel, then please
subscribe and press the bell icon so
that you can keep getting all my latest
insurance-related videos.
And if you like this video, then
definitely share it with your friends because knowledge
increases by sharing. So friends, let's start with
waiting period. So friends,
we understand waiting period in this way
that waiting period is such a thing in which
you have to wait for some disease, that is, wait for
one year, two years, three years, only
after that you will get treatment for that disease.
If we look here
from the consumer point of view, the
roomer is very sad that his policy has a
waiting period in it. If we
think from the company's point of view, then it becomes clear here
that the company is
trying to stop its boss. The company does
not want any person to be loss-making.
So let's understand this.
I have divided it into four categories, so
this will make it clear to you
what a waiting period is and
how this policy works. So
friends, let's talk
about compulsory waiting. You will find a compulsory waiting
period in every company
because this company has a compulsory
waiting period. This is necessary
so that the loss of the policy, which is from the company's point
of view, can be prevented.
Suppose today I have a minor
illness, viral fever, or
dengue fever, pneumonia, or
typhoid. Suppose
I purchase the policy today and I
go to the hospital two days later and get
treatment, then the
company will incur a loss. So, what
all the companies have done is that there is a
compulsory waiting period of 30 days, that is,
you will
get any cover in the policy only after 30 days. But accident is
such a thing that it can happen to you at any time. So, an
accident can happen at any time.  If it is there, then there is a
compulsory waiting period for it. It has been
stated that you
can get your accidental cover from Devan only from day one. Secondly,
friends, there is a waiting period for special dishes,
which is approximately 2 years
in every company. This is because
these diseases do not develop within a day,
such as gall bladder stones,
kidney stones, joint
replacement, hernia, your
appendix operation, etc. So,
these are some such diseases which take
time to develop, friends. And suppose
today I come to know that I have
kidney stones, which I can also control and manage with
medicines in two to four months,
but after that, if I need it, then
this claim will not be available, friends.
Because here every company has a
waiting period of 2 years, but every company has
some exceptions too. There is a Star Health
policy called Young Star, where it is for one
year, there is a Max Bupa policy called Heartbeat.
3198, so friends, companies do
something to promote their product
that gives relaxation in the waiting period. The
third point, if we
talk about pre-existing business, if
you have mentioned in the proposal form or while filling the form that you used to have
any 20 kg disease earlier, it has been
cured now or it is still
digital and the insurance company is
providing you insurance, then it
can impose a waiting period of two to four years on it. Every company has a
different waiting period, here some company reduces it by 2 years,
some by 3 years, some by
4 years, so every company has a
different waiting period for pre-existing diseases,
so whenever you
take a policy and you have deleted any of your diseases, then
you must ask there
whether I will get coverage for this disease, it is mentioned
in the policy certificate
that you will get the cover for this disease
after two years or you will get the cover for this disease
after 3 years, friends, our fourth
point comes  It is about maternity, so
see, maternity is not a disease, it is a
part of family planning, but still
some companies give this option in it to promote their product
because they know that if you are a young couple
and you have taken a policy, then this maternity
cover which is 90% will definitely come and
for that you will have to do it, that is why companies
say that both the couples should be within that policy for
2 years to 30 years and
this policy should be renewed in continuation
and even after that, whenever you get 4 years covered,
then
you will get maternity benefit,
but friends, there are limitations there too,
that you will get 25 to 30 thousand rupees for normal
delivery or about 50 to 60
thousand rupees for C-section, you will
not get more than that and that too when you
take a maternity plan, there is a premium to be paid in it
too, so friends,
all this emphasis on waiting period has been
made so that the companies
can stop their loss-making, if here only the
company  They will give relaxation that suppose if someone becomes
pregnant then anyone will
buy a plan and will go to the
hospital for delivery, then companies have
words there, similarly there is compulsory waiting
period, today you bought a policy and
you go for treatment of any
disease, then that is the glass of the company, so
friends, you should also understand a little that our
customers have to wait, but
if you think from the point of view of the company also, then what
they have here is bigg boss making
business, to stop this this
waiting period is imposed, so two
poets, you must have understood this video
that what is waiting period and
why it is imposed in every policy, if you
liked it then please definitely
share it with your friends and like this video
and thank you very much for watching this video, see you
in the next video